Guide to the Richard Shelton Kirby Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Richard Shelton Kirby papers
1873-1956
MS 1104
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(4 boxes, 1 folio)
Correspondence, writings, and research files reflecting Kirby's interest in the history of engineering. Much of the material was gathered in connection with his book, Engineering in History, published in 1956. Important correspondents are Ludlow S. Bull, an Egyptologist, and his co-autors, Arthur B. Darling, Frederick G. Kilgour, and Sidney Withington.
Kirby, Richard Shelton, 1874-1964
Immediate Source of Acquisition
In part, gift from Richard S. Kirby, 1940s and 1950s, and Dorothy Hooker, 1970.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Richard Shelton Kirby reflect his interest in the history of engineering. A small amount of correspondence with other authors and engineers is included which deals with research questions and comments on engineering issues in their books. The only extended correspondence is with the Egyptologist Ludlow S. Bull (folder 2) concerning engineering in ancient Egypt, and with Kirby's co-authors of Engineering in History, Arthur B. Darling, Frederick G. Kilgour, and Sidney Withington (folder 4). Other letters from friends and colleagues are bound with photographs and newspaper clippings in a retirement volume dedicated to Kirby. An address delivered at his retirement dinner is also included. A number of certificates and diplomas can be found in the folio. There are also four letters addressed to Kirby's father, James Andrew Kirby, concerning a right-of-way and a contract for grading Westchester Avenue in Rye, New York (folder 1).
The remainder of the papers, amounting to two-thirds of the collection, consists of six short writings by Kirby on the history of engineering and research materials used for the most part in preparing Engineering in History, which was published in 1956. Included are notes, photostats, newspaper clippings and other printed matter, and an index card file
Portions of these papers were given to Yale University by Richard Shelton Kirby in the 1940s and 1950s and by Dorothy Hooker in 1970.
Biographical / Historical
Richard S. Kirby (1874-1964): educator; Ph.B., Yale, 1896; C.E., Yale, 1898; instructor in Sanitary Engineering, 1906-1909, Yale; assistant professor of Mechanical Drawing and Descriptive Geometry, 1915-1922; associate professor of Engineering Drawing, 1922-; chairman of the Department of Engineering Drawing, 1933-.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Engineering -- Study and teaching; Educators; Engineers; Bull, Ludlow Seguine, 1886-1954; Darling, Arthur B. (Arthur Burr), 1892-1971; Kilgour, Frederick G.; Kirby, Richard Shelton, 1874-1964; Withington, Sidney, 1884-; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Dept. of Engineering and Applied Science
- Inventory, 1873-1956, undated; 1.25 linear feet (4 boxes)
  - James Andrew Kirby: letters, 1873-1890 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Richard Shelton Kirby
    - Correspondence
      - Adams, Samuel Hopkins, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Bull, Ludlow S., 1928-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Burt, Maxwell Struthers, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Chase, Mary Ellen, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Dickinson, H.W., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - DuBois, A.J., 1898 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - duMaurier, Daphne, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Freeman, Douglas Southall, 1946, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Langdon, William C., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Lewars, Elsie Singmaster, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Looney, Charles T.G., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Morrow, Honoré Willsie, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Richter, Conrad, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Taft, L., 1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Taft, William H., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Williamson, S.T., 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Woodward, W.E., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence concerning Engineering in History, 1939-1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Memorabilia
      - Scarpbook of letters, newspaper clippings, and photographs entitled "To Richard Kirby from some friends at Yale", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Address by Hardy Cross at farewell dinner for R.S.K., 1943 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Certificates and diplomas, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        General
        See also: CF26
    - Writings
      - "Some Engineering Pioneering"; with published version. "Some Engineering Beginnings," Civil Engineering, [post-1932], 1937 November (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Review of Oliver Evans: a Chronicle of Early American Early American Engineering, by Greville Bathe and Dorothy Bathe, [1935?] (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - "Some Pioneer Engineers" (lectures), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - "Henri Pitot, Pioneeer in Practical Hydraulics," Civil Engineering, 1939 December (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - "Specifications and Plans of Ancient Times," Civil Engineering, 1941 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - "Engineer During the French Revolution", undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Research materials
      - Reprints and pamphlets re: engineering, highways, etc., 1938-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Statistics on motor traffic in Paris, [pre-1941] (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Engineering in History
        - "Memos on Chapter 1 and 2", [pre-1956] (Box 1, Folder 16)
        - "Chapter 4. The Middle Ages. Working Note", [pre-1956] (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
        - "Chapter 5. The Renaissance", [pre-1956] (Box 1, Folder 19)
        - "Chapter 6. Sidney Withington notes", [pre-1956] (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
        - "Chap.7. Rails. S. Withington notes", [pre-1956] (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
        - "Chap. 8. Steel. Notes", [pre-1956] (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
        - "Pargellis mss.", [pre-1956] (Box 2, Folder 26)
        - Miscellaneous, [pre-1956] (Box 2, Folder 27)
        - Index card file, [pre-1956] (Box 3)
        - Index card file, pre-1956 (Box 4)
  - Diplomas and certificates
    - Yale University diploma, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Union Free School diploma, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Connecticut Society of Civil Engineers honorary membership certificate, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Marriage certificate of James Andrew Kirby, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 26)